Previously on The Institute...
- The fuck is that?
- Nobody knows.
Happens every week or so.
The Red Steps Tragedy?
Yeah. Annie was obsessed with it.
"Notre Pain." It's some
weird inside joke they all had.
We never understood it.
Stay away from Route 10.
What? The research place?
The infectious-disease whatever it is?
- Harry!
- Shut up!
Harry Cross and the Wilcox girls
are resting comfortably
and expected to make a full recovery.
We're all fucking kids here.
I can't do anything.
I'm a glorified janitor.
You're stronger than you think, Maureen.
Some of your test scores
aren't corroborating
with the progress...
you're clearly making.
Maybe because the tests are bullshit,
and so is this place, and so are you,
with all due respect.
I'm not the enemy, Luke.
You've been working with
Luke Ellis off-the-books.
It was Stackhouse's idea.
He's the one who told me to keep going.
What about Ellis?
What about him?
We still need to
find a way to prove he's TP.
Leave that to me.
Yeah, pretty much all they do
is gather us for Movie Nights.
Last night, we were brushing
our teeth, then we were driving,
then we were doing 'doctor stuff',
like checking in on patients,
giving injections, that sort of thing.
Something's wrong inside her head.
Movie nights take a toll.
First, they'll have her lead
a Sparkler night.
And then, they'll move her to Recovery.
That's where The Hum's coming from.
Okay. I gotta go.
Luke, I know what's behind that door,
the one that Sha showed us.
I saw it in Maureen's head.
* Shout, shout *
* Let it all out *
* These are the things
I can do without *
* Come on *
* I'm talking to you *
* In violent times *
* You shouldn't have to sell your soul *
* In black and white *
* They really, really ought to know *
* Shout, shout *
* Let it all out *
* These are the things
I can do without *
* Come on *
* I'm talking to you *
She's the survivor
from last night's incident?
Hendricks said
that, uh, she gorked out early.
Something about, uh,
the psychic bond with her sister
being violently severed.
That's a new one.
Uh, anyway,
um, Sigsby figures
that there's still
some juice worth squeezing.
Hmm.
Uh, is there anything I can do for you?
Now that you mention it, would
you mind taking out the trash?
We're short-staffed back here.
I'd appreciate the help.
Okay.
We weren't expecting him
to kick out
for at least another day or so.
Denny's already in there,
getting it ready.
He'll help you load.
Get the door.
Okay?
- Yeah.
- All right, on three.
Okay. One, two, three.
Watch your wrist.
We all go up the chimney here.
No.
'Cause I'm not gonna let that happen.
Send the Ellis kid in.
Luke.
Have you ever heard the phrase
"Veritas liberabit vos?"
"The truth will set you free."
Hmm.
So, are you, um,
finally setting me free?
An intellect like yours can be...
a blessing or a curse.
In your case,
it just makes everything harder.
Dr. Hendricks and I believe you're TP.
I wish. 'Cause the sooner I am,
the sooner I go home.
Right?
This... This isn't the place for lying.
Luke, remember, you're here to serve,
not just your country
but the whole world.
Does that ever sound just
a little grandiose to you?
I mean, what does that even mean?
Serving the entire world?
You'll have to trust me.
Trust is earned.
It certainly is.
The truth at last.
What did you do? You killed them!
- Hey, let her go now!
- Why did you do that?
What did you do?
Oh, you'll wish you hadn't done that.
Get off me!
Get off!
- Julia.
- One sec.
Get off!
This is a teachable moment.
Julia, we have a problem.
Get off me!
Sigsby! Sigsby!
Can I help you, sir?
Sure hope so.
I'm Dennison's new night knocker.
- How are you?
- Hm. Night knocker, huh?
Well, that's a new one on me.
It's really just a night watchman.
You know, "Two o'clock and all is well."
Hmm. So you came all the way
out here from Dennison
to make sure all is well?
Oh, no. I'm sure
you guys got that covered.
Not back on shift till sundown tomorrow.
Like I said, I'm new to town.
Thought it was gonna
be nice weather for a hike,
but I think I must've got
kind of turned around here.
So there's a man at the gate. So what?
He's the new Dennison night knocker,
the one I told you about.
The one who was talking
to the crazy woman.
Yeah.
Is this the Institute up there?
People in town, they talk about
it like it's the Wonka factory.
What exactly goes on in there, man?
Infectious disease research.
Really?
You don't always see barbed wire
on the inside of a fence.
Well, you know, we have test animals.
People are real uptight nowadays
about security protocols,
lab leaks, all that shit.
We should've taken him out, too.
You agreed it wasn't a problem
unless she mentioned us.
Well, clearly, it's a problem.
It's a lot of security for a lab.
Well, state of the world nowadays.
Fences and walls,
good guys keeping the bad guys out.
I imagine the...
hard part is keeping straight who's who.
He disappears.
The cops'll figure you hire a drifter,
sooner or later, he keeps drifting.
Bodies bring attention.
You're awful quick to pull the trigger.
- Better safe than sorry.
- Exactly.
- Meaning?
- He's a physically conditioned,
military-aged male.
He fits the profile.
He could be anything.
Investigative journalist.
Undercover FBI.
Killing him could create
more problems than it solves.
He could be from Upstairs,
sent to test us.
Shit.
You got a ride back to town, sir?
You know what?
I think I might've parked,
actually, just down that road.
Yeah, well, you have a good day, sir.
Yeah.
You, too.
We need to find out who he really is.
Yeah. Then we kill him.
So, the Avester told us
about your parents.
I'm so sorry, Luke.
Me, too. It's fucked.
I want you to take a hit of this, okay?
- No.
- Oh, come on.
Can't let these fuckers win, Luke.
They already have. It's over.
No way. We can still get out of here.
Get out and go where?
I don't have anywhere to go anymore.
Welcome to the fucking club, dude.
I've never had anywhere to go,
but anywhere is better than here.
What's the point in fighting
if you know you can't win?
Sometimes you win just by showing them
you're still willing to fight.
Yeah? Look where that got you. Hmm?
There's a chance. You never know
what might happen.
We need you. Kalisha needs you.
I can't help you. We're all just kids.
What the fuck are we supposed to do?
We can find a way to get revenge
on that fucking bitch Sigsby,
on this whole fucking place, man.
Please, Luke. Please.
Look, I've been thinking
about what you said
about those motion cameras
in the hallway,
how they can detect your body heat...
I don't care, Nicky.
I figure if we can get
into the AC closet,
maybe we can find a way
to raise the temperature enough
to produce that, you know,
"motion white-out"
you were talking about.
It's all bullshit, man.
Even that closet
has got the electrical
sensory lock on it, so...
Cameras pointed at it,
so it's... not gonna happen.
Attention, Front Half!
Please join us in the cafeteria
for Nicky's graduation party.
Yay.
Chef Doug has made
a special carrot cake.
We hear that's Nicky's favorite.
Well, that's our cue.
Coming?
You should come.
I'm planning something. You'll dig it.
* Goodbye Front Half for you *
* Goodbye Front Half, dear Nicky *
Whoo!
Cake's really good.
You should have some.
I don't want to eat anything.
I just keep thinking
I'm gonna... wake up.
Luke.
Don't die here.
Don't let me die here. We're too young.
Young and beautiful, right?
Didn't want to be the one to say it.
All right.
Mr. Wilholm, congratulations!
Time to go.
Why don't you tell them
the truth about this place?
that none of us are ever
getting out of here alive?
More of Nicky's conspiracies.
We know about the chimneys.
We know what happens in Back Half.
Move.
Where do you think you're going?
Stop what you're doing!
Do your fucking job!
You little prick!
Stop it! Leave him alone!
Nicky!
No!
Fuck you! Fuck all of you!
You fucking pussies!
Stop.
Stop!
Wow. How many men does it take
to restrain one teenage boy?
But he wasn't even that mad.
Nicky wasn't that mad?
Shh, shh, shh, shh, shh.
Yeah. He was doing it for you...
and for George and Sha.
You okay?
They're sending me to Back Half soon.
I thought your TP tests
were still inconclusive.
No. Not anymore.
So if you're still willing
to help me get out of here,
the time is now.
Did you know...
that they murdered my parents?
What makes you think that?
I don't think it. I know it.
And I know you, Maureen.
You're better than this.
You hate it as much as we do.
I can't. They'll kill me.
What if it was your son in here?
Stop it, Luke, please.
If Jake were here, would you
just stand back and let him die?
Hi.
Did you find that stuff
that I asked for?
Well, how's my car? Did you gas it up?
What?
Uh, no. Sorry.
I, uh...
Again, I appreciate you
letting me borrow it.
I'm glad to know that you trust me.
Let's say I'm still on the fence.
Although I certainly do seem to
be risking a lot on your hunch.
You know what the Chief'll do
if he finds out I took these?
Nothing's supposed
to leave the Records room.
I know, and, uh, thank you,
really.
It's... it's not just a hunch.
There is something very wrong
with Annie's death,
and I am gonna find out what.
Hate to quote the Chief,
but that's not your job anymore.
Somebody's getting away with something,
and maybe it is just Annie,
but maybe it's something more.
And I just...
Look, job or not, I guess...
I'm just not the kinda guy
who can look the other way.
Guess you at least
get points for self-awareness.
Mostly building permits.
Honestly, woulda thought
there'd be more.
This is the part where you tell
me why we need all this stuff.
What did you find up there?
Notre Pain.
Like from the yearbook?
Mm-hmm.
Nobody could ever figure out
what Zoe Sloane
and the other kids were doing
at the Red Steps, right?
I mean, they knew that it was dangerous.
They knew there were many people
who drowned up there.
Well, they were drunk.
We figured it must have been
a dare or something.
Well, what if they were
never there that night?
What if they didn't die there?
What if that's just what...
What if that's just
where they found their bodies?
Who'd wanna...
Anybody ever really,
really look into the Institute?
I mean, like the Chief
or Inspections or anything?
Pretty sure it's federal.
We don't have jurisdiction.
Okay, well, right, um, here,
that is where the old fence collapsed.
When I went up there,
I was looking around
and there was
a big "no trespassing" sign
with a bunch of letters missing.
Guess what it says now.
"Notre Pain"?
- Mm-hmm.
- You think
that's where Zoe Sloane
and her friends went that night.
I don't know.
But it's...
I wasn't sure whether to show you this.
Two weeks after the Red Steps kids died,
the Institute broke ground
on a new perimeter fence.
It wasn't just a new fence.
It was a whole new fire road.
Before the new fence went up,
they would have a clear shot all
the way down to the Institute.
Being a teenager around here
is lethally boring.
Even if this is right,
there won't be
any evidence anymore, so...
We're not looking for evidence.
No? That's not something
that big-city cops have to worry about?
Sometimes we do.
Sometimes we just kind
of... poke the bear
until something comes back at us.
What'd you do?
Hopefully,
I put myself on their radar.
I'm... I'm sorry about earlier, Maureen.
I shouldn't have asked you to do it.
How would you do it, get out of here?
Do you have a plan?
The chain link, uh,
in the yard in Back Half,
there's a piece of it that's
come away from the foundation.
I just don't have a way
to get there, so...
Can you get to the laundry room
without anyone seeing you?
I would need a key card
for the elevator.
Say I got you one.
What about the cameras?
We think we have a way around it.
Okay.
I can't take you
all the way to the fence,
but I can get you close.
Be in the laundry room by 11:30,
not a minute later.
Okay. Yeah.
Make sure I get it back.
They freak out over a missing card.
Total lockdown.
And, um, the...
Oh.
Sorry. It's all I could find.
Get Maureen in here.
Come here. Here you go.
A little melon for ya.
Come on. It's your favorite.
Oh, yeah. There you go. There you go.
Oh, Tim Jamieson, speak of the Devil.
Mr. Hollister,
it's my night off, so I just...
Fella here to see you.
Trevor Stackhouse.
Tim Jamieson.
What can I do for you, Mr. Stackhouse?
I run security for the place
you were sniffing around this afternoon.
Ah. The Institute.
That's the one.
Is there somewhere we can talk?
[ma Right, but where on the flowchart...
...first door is after.
You guys are useless.
Look at this. If you just look at it,
visually you'll see.
Figure out bird, then flowers...
Hey, what the fuck? I'm watching that.
- I wanna watch cartoons!
- Wait your turn!
I wanna watch cartoons!
Hey!
Ahh! I wanna watch cartoons!
Hey! Break it up! Now!
Enough! Enough!
- I wanna watch cartoons!
- Break it up!
Break it up!
No! Cartoons!
Cartoons!
- I wanna watch cartoons!
- Break it up!
- Cartoons!
- You took my turn!
- Enough!
- I get to watch cartoons!
That's enough!
How long were you with Boston PD?
Fifteen years.
Good long stretch.
You didn't wanna finish out your 20,
qualify for a full pension?
It was time for a change.
Yeah.
Makes me wonder, how's a fella
like you become a night knocker
in a town like this?
I read about
the Westfield Mall incident.
Must weigh heavy on a man,
shoot a boy that young.
Appears you have me at a disadvantage.
An instructor of mine used to say,
"Always pays to know the other
guy more than he knows you."
Instructor in what?
How did you come to be outside
our place this afternoon?
Your place?
Well, like I said to your guy, I was...
Hiking. Yeah.
Exploring your new environs.
That's right.
Plus, I've been getting up
to speed on my local history.
You wouldn't happen
to have been working there
back in '08 when those kids drowned?
I was.
- Terrible thing.
- Mm-hmm.
Friend of mine
has a theory about those kids,
that they never
went swimming that night,
that they actually got caught
breaking into your place.
Bunch of bored small-town kids
looking for adventure, you know.
And what did your friend say
happened next?
I'm on the edge of my seat.
You interview everyone who shows
up at the gate, Mr. Stackhouse?
Especially the ones
with military backgrounds.
We're a popular target
for conspiracy theorists.
Used to be, we'd ignore them,
but in the age of social media,
that only allows them to fester.
We've decided it best
to confront them directly.
Speaking of, I'd be happy
to talk to your friend,
see if I can't put her at ease.
Well, you can't.
She's dead.
Oh.
Pity.
Well, Mr. Jamieson, if you have
any questions in the future
about our operation,
please don't hesitate to reach out.
Thanks.
I won't.
What do you have for me?
Well, um, obviously,
Harry and the twins
threw everyone for a loop,
and then the unpleasantness
with Nicky's departure...
Maureen, Maureen!
Luke Ellis. what do you have for me?
After Nicky's graduation,
he said something
that upset you, you walked away...
He believes we killed his parents.
I thought we don't do that.
We try not to. We really do.
But his mother woke during the snatch,
so...
collateral damage.
Have you developed an attachment to him?
Of course not.
Have you ever?
No.
I'm proud to say I haven't.
You know the protocol
for undue attachment:
stay away from Front Half
until Luke graduates, and,
in the meantime, go home.
But it's a Sparkler Night,
and I'm supposed to assist.
Then, I need to change the Back Half...
Fine. Finish your shift.
But stay awake from Luke Ellis.
Copy that.
What are you...
Twenty-two grams of protein.
You'll need it.
All right, gentlemen, ladies,
you know the drill.
Please take your positions.
So this is movie night, huh?
Doesn't look like much.
Come on, man.
As a matter of fact, Mr. Wilholm,
you have the good luck to be joining us
on a Sparkler night.
Okay. What's the difference?
Movie night's training. This is real.
This is why you're here.
This is your mission.
Everything you do is in service of this.
Great.
I'd hate to think it
was all for nothing.
You know, I've never seen you
leave your office before
except for graduations.
Figured maybe you didn't want
to see how the sausage is made.
Hmm.
Guess this really is a big night, huh?
Seeing as how you haven't had
any time to acclimate,
we won't expect you to pull
much weight tonight.
Just sit back and ride the wave,
as they say.
I'm sure Ms. Benson will
be happy to talk you through it.
Don't sweat it.
You'll just And I ju feel like you're...
getting pulled along
with the rest of us.
Pulled along where?
Ms. Stanhope will be
our conductor tonight.
Conductor. Like on a train?
Yes. Or an orchestra.
Or perhaps an electrical wire.
It means I'm the lucky girl
who gets to stay awake.
I'm sorry. Awake?
Not like sleep.
Although you do black out and...
you do feel better after.
The headache dials it down some.
- For a while.
- Bottom line:
say your goodbyes.
After tonight, Iris is going home.
After Recovery.
Of course. Congratulations.
I'm ready.
Whatever happens, no more headaches.
So you've got that going for you,
which is nice.
Which is nice.
Ladies, gentlemen,
it's time to get started.
Here we go.
All right, everyone, you know the drill.
Time to give yourselves over.
Mr. Wilholm, that means
you lean into The Hum,
nothing else. Let it carry you.
The conductor is the only one
who stays present.
Never been much for giving myself over.
Well, in this case,
I advise you to rethink,
for your own safety.
Just close your eyes.
Ms. Stanhope,
you still with us?
You have control?
I think so. I can feel him breathing.
The bottle you're looking for
is marked fentanyl citrate.
All the bottles are marked in Russian.
The doctor can read them.
That means you can read them.
All right.
Yes.
Tony, can you confirm
they're in the flow?
Confirmed.
Where are you?
Are you... driving?
I know I said just a couple of hours...
Oh, that's just great.
So, you're stealing my fucking car?
- I'm not. Please...
- Mom always says I'm drawn
to unreliable men. She blames my dad.
Wendy, will you listen to me, please?
Look, I get why
you would still be
unsure about all of it...
Annie, the Red Steps thing, me.
But I know that they killed Annie.
Oh, God. What's happened?
This guy came to see me,
said he was their head of security.
Well, what'd he want?
Warn me off.
Well, maybe that's not a bad idea.
Yeah, well, I'm sorry about the car.
I will have it back
to you by the morning.
Where have I heard that before?
Where are you going?
The Red Steps, I guess.
- Back to Notre Pain.
- You know what the Chief'll do?
He's already pissed.
I get it, Wendy. Try not to worry, okay?
I'll be fine.
Just, uh, be careful.
I will.
Iris.
Iris?
Jesus, you're acting like
you've never seen this before.
All the bullshit in this place.
We still... manage
to keep the trains running.
Not somehow.
You.
Please.
No, really.
I hope Upstairs realize how
lucky they are to have you.
I know you're still mad at me,
and you have every right to be.
I just...
I wish we could celebrate,
like always.
All conscripts stable.
'Kay.
Get these kids cleaned up.
Get 'em in bed.
- Good work, everybody.
- Yeah.
Front Half store closet.
Ten minutes.
Did your...
Do your parents ever read the Bible?
Oh, yeah. A lot.
But they were always feeling
a lot of other things,
things they weren't a-sposed to.
You know who Samson was?
Yeah, with the hair?
The Philistines bribed
his girlfriend to cut it
to take away his strength.
That's right.
And after the Philistines
took him prisoner,
Samson prayed...
for the first time in his life.
He prayed that he would be able
to regain enough of his strength
to get his revenge.
And when they brought
him to their temple
to show they'd conquered him,
he brought the whole place
down on top of them.
Was he still inside the temple
when he pulled it down?
Yeah. But...
he still won.
"Sometimes you win
just by showing you're
still willing to fight."
We're gonna do more than that.
We're gonna bring this whole place down.
Almost time.
Hope it's hot enough.
Okay. Maureen's headed back.
Sigsby and Stackhouse
are on their way to storage.
The enemy will provide the means
of his own defeat, right?
I don't know what that means.
It means...
we have to turn their strengths
into weaknesses.
Okay.
It's time. Let's do it.
There you go.
Come on.
Oh, gosh. Oh, gosh.
Hey.
I'm gonna stretch the lobe.
You open the scissors
and get them into position.
Oh gosh.
Come on, Avery.
I... It's just...
- I can't do it.
- Avery, you have to.
Please. I'm sorry. There's no way.
Okay, we don't have time for this.
No.
Oh, gosh. Oh, gosh.
Oh, gosh.
Here.
Oh, gosh. Oh, gosh.
I wish you could take me
with you. I wish it bad.
I know. Me, too.
Don't forget about us.
Never.
Okay. Oh, God.
Up and at 'em, Ms. Sigsby.
Don't miss the fun.
Well, after the other day,
I was afraid we'd...
Anyway, uh...
I'm glad we could put
the unpleasantness behind us.
Slow down. We're only here
so that if Stackhouse checks his feed,
he'll know we're sticking to routine.
Oh.
Um, you okay?
- You need some ice?
- I'm fine.
Luke Ellis, your pet project, did this.
I'm sending his ass
to the Back Half tomorrow.
No, Julia. I need more time with him.
The coast is clear.
Good luck, Luke.
Thanks, Avester. You, too.
Hold on. There's someone coming.
Stay back. Hide behind the corner.
Thanks. That was close.
Give it two more seconds.
'Kay. He's in the cafeteria.
Everything looks good in the lunchroom.
Where are you? I can't see you.
Yeah, I'm right
in the middle of the room.
Can you wave your hand
in front of the lens?
Nothing's happening.
These fucking cameras need an overhaul.
They're not detecting motion.
Must be the heat.
Fucking sauna.
Hang tight.
I'll let you know when it's safe to go.
Okay, you can go.
Do you realize how important
this could be for the program?
The program's down
three recruits since last night.
The Back Half needs bodies.
Your ambitions will have to go on hold.
Julia.
That should be enough time.
If he's been paying attention,
he should know that
you don't last that long.
Oh, no!
No, no, no, no, no, no, no!
Julia, wait.
What I said before about Upstairs,
I wasn't just blowing smoke.
They really are lucky to have you.
I just...
You were a minute and a half late.
Well, I-I would...
No, but...
All right.
You're clear to the laundry room.
Ms. Sigsby.
Maureen.
- All's well?
- Yes, ma'am.
Glad to hear it.
- Luke?
- Maureen.
Cart. In you go.
We don't have much time.
They know my schedule.
Never stops, huh?
Uh, gorks do make a mess.
Yeah, tell me about it. Hey, listen,
gonna take one of these towels.
Need a shower before I head out.
Check the laundry room.
Come on. I'm in a rush.
Me and Zeke got a liberty.
Gonna head out to
that truck stop on 116,
buy ourself a couple lot lizards.
They're already running low back there.
When Sigsby asks why they're
even lower than they're
supposed to be,
I'll make sure to tell her why.
It's one fucking towel.
Go fuck yourself, Maureen.
Okay, Luke, end of the line.
Here.
Okay.
I've just unlocked the door.
The next one's not locked either.
That'll get you out into the backyard.
Once you're past the fence,
just head downhill right to the river.
You're gonna have to cross that river
and then walk downstream
until you get to the Red Steps.
It's a picnic spot.
I'll come and pick you up
once I'm off shift.
Then where do we go?
I-I know a reporter.
They're gonna tell your story.
What is this?
Show the world what goes on here.
We're gonna show the world together.
Don't worry about me.
I just wish I never saw this place.
Thank you, Maureen, really.
Okay. Good luck, Luke.
Okay.
Okay, you... you better go.
Iris?
Jesus Christ.
Hey, hey, hey, hey. Iris, it's okay.
No, no, no, no, no, no.
We're gonna get you out of here.
Okay?
Iris, please.
I'm sorry.