Previously on The Institute...
Look, kid, you're
pretty banged up.
We should probably get you
to a doctor or hospital.
No, no, no. I don't
have time for that.
I need to get to a place
called the Red Steps.
Do you know it?
I know how it sounds.
You think I'm having some
sort of break with reality
or maybe the beginnings
of schizophrenia.
I didn't say that. I
know Stackhouse is real.
The rest of it is
a little weird.
Zeke, where exactly is the
locater on subject Ellis?
[Zeke] What do you mean, ma'am?
I'm showing him directly
in front of you.
-[sighs]
-There's a chance,
if we bring the boy
back quickly enough,
we never have to make the call.
If we bring him back alive.
Easy, easy.
[gasps]
Chief, this boy needs help.
What happened to him?
The kid's got a flash drive,
says it'll help
back up his story.
I have eyes on the boy.
Some kind of video.
Well, I guess we'd
better watch it.
["Shout" performed by
The Lumineers plays]
♪♪♪
♪ Shout, shout ♪
♪ Let it all out ♪
♪ These are the things
I can do without ♪
♪ Come on ♪
♪ I'm talking to you ♪
♪ In violent times ♪
♪ You shouldn't have
to sell your soul ♪
♪ In black and white ♪
♪ They really, really
ought to know ♪
♪ Shout, shout ♪
♪ Let it all out ♪
♪ These are the things
I can do without ♪
♪ Come on ♪
♪ I'm talking to you ♪
♪♪♪
Oh, God. Hope this works.
I'll never be strong
enough to do this again.
Luke, if you're watching this,
it means that you're out,
and I'm dead.
So...
I-I'm gonna hide
this in my uniform.
I made a hole.
I'm gonna record everything,
so you can show the world.
[breathing unsteadily]
My life story doesn't matter.
I'm going to hell anyway.
I knew that 20 years
ago in Afghanistan.
[elevator beeping]
Just... I'm sorry it
took me too long to see.
[elevator beeping]
You don't think of
yourself as evil.
It's still hard for me to
believe what we've done.
All in service of this
thing they created.
This machine they've
made has needs.
[mysterious music]
And, of course,
the biggest need is a
constant supply of children.
[metallic thudding]
[beeping]
Because Back Half uses them up.
By the time they hit
Recovery, they're gone.
Kaput.
'Gorked', we say.
Eventually, they just
forget to keep breathing.
Recovery.
We call it Gorky Park.
Oh, my God.
Sometimes, you
just make jokes...
trying to stay sane.
And this is where
they all end up.
No. No, no, no.
Dust to dust.
No one thinks of
themselves as evil.
[whirring]
[flames whooshing]
Nobody should have to...
Well, uh...
now you know.
What in the name of all that
is holy did I just watch?
Where the hell
have you been, son?
-What's our ETA?
-Thirty minutes.
-Target confirmed?
-Yeah.
Our asset says the boy is
still inside the station.
He neutralized one of
Stackhouse's people already.
[Nina] Who?
Uh, one of his sleepers.
-So, we're going in hot.
-Yes.
You're cleared to go in hot.
Just recover the kid.
Keep our asset in place.
If there are problems?
Then... we deep clean.
And just be aware, the
night-knocker's ex-Army;
he's gonna be on high alert.
Well, at least he
won't be too smart.
What does that mean?
I just mean, like,
Yeah. My dad's 26
years career army.
He has a doctorate and three
master's degrees, so...
My friends are all still
there. We need to hurry,
and we can save them,
but we need to go now.
Look around you, kid.
This department is not built
to hit a place like that.
It's a hard target. You
would need a SWAT Team.
-Or three.
-Every day, kids are dying.
-We-we can't waste more time.
-What do you think happens
if the Chief goes in
there with two officers.
-It's not just...
-[Drew] Hello? Chief?
You back there?
Hey, what's up with
the phones? I heard...
Drew, I need you
to mind the shop.
People are gonna call
about the cell service,
the Internet, and
God knows what else.
-But what's going on?
-[Ashworth] You're in charge.
I'm taking these two
to Portland right now.
I know the SAC down there...
Special Agent in Charge.
He's a good guy, rock solid.
And this... whatever
the hell this is,
I will tell you one thing. It
is way above our purview here.
-Let's go.
-I can drive them, sir.
-I'm happy to go.
-No, you stay here.
Get Wendy in. All hands on deck.
Uh, yeah, uh, Chief, please.
I-I don't wanna...
Why don't I take them?
I don't wanna be in charge.
What if there's an emergency?
There's no Comms. I won't
be able to reach you.
Get Wendy in. The two
of you can handle it.
I'm gonna walk this in myself.
They're not gonna take
you seriously otherwise.
We're gonna get
you some help, kid.
[gun firing]
Shit! Damn it!
Goddamn it!
[groaning]
Don't fuck with me, Jamieson!
Don't fuck with me!
Drew... Drew, I am...
I am not going to fuck with you.
I never meant to do that.
[breathing unsteadily]
Get his cuffs.
Drew, just... just take a
second. Think about what...
Tim, I have known
the Chief 20 years,
and look what I just did to
him. I've known you how long?
Two fucking months?
Now, get his cuffs. Now!
All right, all right. All right.
Good.
Now, take the cuffs and
lock the kid to the bench.
He's the one they want.
Now! Go! Go!
You think I'm fucking around?
[exhaling sharply]
-Sorry, kid.
-[cuffs clicking]
[cuffs clicking]
Okay, now, do yourself,
next to him, so I can keep
an eye on both of you.
Do it right! I'm watching you.
[cuffs clicking]
Okay. Good. Good.
Under control.
[phone beeping, ringing]
[phone ringing]
This is Reynolds. I've got them.
Both of them?
-Yes.
-Excellent.
[knocking]
Hang on.
Yes, sir.
We just may live
through this yet.
-You wanted to see me.
-We're gonna have to move
the Dixon boy up, quick
and dirty. Use the Tank.
This is a bad idea.
It's a terrible idea. He's
too much of a wild card.
He's so strong in some
ways, I'd worry...
I have the Keyhole in two
hours. If we can't make it,
there's gonna be
problems. Just do it.
Now!
[exhaling sharply]
[door opening]
You still there?
[Drew] I'm here.
I have a team 20 minutes out.
I need you to
control the situation
until they reinforce you.
Yeah. I can do that.
Now what?
You wouldn't happen to have...
a safety pin or a
paperclip, would you?
No.
Uh, there was a bit of a, uh...
a complication. Uh...
I had to... [clearing throat]
Chief Ashworth is dead.
Understood.
The team will take care of that.
Okay. Uh...
Now, listen to me, Reynold...
Um, okay.
I need you to lock
down that place
until backup arrives.
No one in. No one out.
I can't stress that enough.
Lock it down.
No one is going anywhere.
Um... No, I understand.
Locked down. Yeah.
Sure.
ETA 20 minutes.
Twenty minutes.
Got it. I'll uh...
Yeah, I-I'll wait here.
Just send them to the side
door, and I'll let them in.
[phone beeping]
Just hang tight.
Okay? Just hang tight.
You don't wanna do this.
Well, it's a bit
late for that, Tim.
Day late and a dollar
short for that.
You're making a huge
fucking mistake, man.
[gasping]
[sighing] I can't look
at this shit anymore.
[groaning]
[grunting]
[straining]
[exhaling sharply]
Shit, the, um, the drive thing.
The fucking video's
in his pocket.
Shit.
[drew grunting]
That, uh... that thing
you did with the tree?
You think... you think you
might be able to try it
with those paperclips?
No, no, I told you. I can't.
I can't control that, okay?
It happens when I'm
upset or if I'm angry.
Well, then, get fucking upset
because if we die, then there's
no one to blow the whistle,
and your fucking friends
are gonna be stuck there.
So, just try.
Are you doing it?
I can't.
Come on. You've got this.
One more time. Let's go.
[inhaling sharply]
[tense music]
Fuck.
Argh! Goddamn it.
Oh, shit. I did not
think that would work.
[grunting]
Couldn't have got
it a little closer?
You do it next time.
[breathing unsteadily]
[Tim] Yes!
[tires screeching]
[car doors closing]
-[pounding]
-About time.
What? No.
No, no, no, no!
They were right...
They were right here! They
were cuffed right here!
-Get the car.
-[Drew] No, I... What the...
Get the car!
They couldn't have gotten far.
Fuck.
[breathing heavily]
[door opening, chiming]
Officer Jamieson! My savior!
Mr. Dobira, I didn't realize
you were out of the hospital.
As I told my brother,
work is its own medicine.
Is there trouble?
-We need your help, sir.
-Of course.
I owe you my life.
Whatever I have is yours.
Do you have a car by any chance?
[stammering]
Or maybe a phone that works.
My phone isn't working,
either. W-Why is that?
-[tires screeching]
-What's going on?
-Oh, shit. Hide us?
-[Obira] Yes, yes. This way!
To the back.
Under there. Under there.
Head around back.
We may need a wider
cordon around the area.
-Hello there.
-May I help you?
We're looking for a...
a boy, a young boy.
It's possible he's
being trafficked.
Are you the police?
Uh, federal officers.
We believe he could be
with a Tim Jamieson,
the new night-knocker.
Do you know him?
I have seen them.
They... they were just here.
They bought coffee and
sandwiches and then they left.
Excuse me, ma'am.
Insurance doesn't allow
customers in that area.
Mr. Jamieson said they
were driving to Portland.
-What kind of car?
-Uh, black.
They're headed to
Portland. Route 1 South.
Your phone is working.
What's going on with
the phones, Officer?
What kind of black car?
Dodge.
Charger, I think.
[engine revving]
[footsteps creaking]
They're gone. It's okay.
Hey.
Thank you.
Wait!
Ilko wada jir bey
wax ku goo ya an.
"Together, the teeth can cut."
When we unite, we are strong.
I kiss my children good
night because of you.
[dramatic music]
[straining]
[groaning]
[powering down]
[gasping]
Apologies, Mr. Dixon,
but we have less than
two hours to Keyhole.
Hope you got your diaper
strapped up tight.
[powering up]
[air hissing]
[groaning]
[gasping]
[straining]
[breathing heavily]
[powering down]
[Avery, telepathically]
No more. No more.
No more. No more!
Avery.
What's going on?
[gasping]
-Luke?
-No. It's fine.
We should go.
-[Tim] Sure?
-Let's go.
I guess I don't need to
tell you what happens
if that kid gets out
of jamming range,
manages to find someone
who'll listen to his story.
No.
Upstairs'll send a burn team.
Expunge us from the
face of the earth.
Delete our birth
certificates. It'll be...
be like we never existed.
We'll catch them.
What... What are we doing, man?
We... We need a plan. We
can't just sneak around.
This is the plan. Shh.
-More cops?
-It's okay.
-[car door opens, closes]
-I trust her.
-Let's move.
-[door closes]
Oh, God.
Have you, uh...
Has anything like this ever...
No.
It's remarkable.
Truly remarkable.
Hey, my friend, are you there?
-[mumbling]
-That's right. That's right.
All right.
-[radio beeping]
-Chief, this is Wendy.
Mic check?
[radio beeping]
Dennison PD, mic
check? Come back.
[sighing]
Anyone, anyone,
anyone, signal check?
[whispering] Wendy.
It's okay. It's okay. It's me.
-[sighing]
-It's me.
You nearly gave
me a heart attack.
Sorry. We, uh...
we've got no place else to go.
What are you doing
here? Who's this?
Did you... God, did you
hit him with my car?
I don't know how
to tell you this.
Chief Ashworth is dead.
-What?
-[Tim] Drew shot him.
What are you talking about?
I am telling you, the Chief
is dead, we are in trouble,
and we need your help right now.
Well, who is this?
-Reynolds.
-[Drew] Yes.
Find a place to
pull over up ahead.
And... And start thinking about
where they might have gone,
who Jamieson has that
he still might trust.
-Okay. Got it.
-Yeah.
You're gonna pull
over behind him.
I'm going back to Dennison.
You keep going, keep
the pressure on,
drive 'em into the cordon.
You're going back?
Yeah.
That clerk, uh...
Also, kids tend to hide
when they're scared,
not run.
[tires squealing]
[Wendy] Looks like there's
more to the article.
Yeah, that's... what loaded
before it all went dead.
Tim? Says he's a
person of interest.
I was kidnapped.
[sighing] I'm so sorry, Luke.
It's awful. Beyond.
God, you need medical
attention, psychological care,
social services.
What are you doing? I
mean, this is... this is...
-You've got no legal...
-I-I had no choice! All right?
If you had seen what
was on that drive...
The drive you left in
the Chief's pocket!
The one that would
prove everything!
-Yeah, I... I know how it sounds.
-Sounds like Annie!
Yeah, and they
fucking killed Annie!
Look, if none of this is real,
who's jamming your
communications?
Uh, landlines,
Internet, cell service.
Who can do all of that?
Yeah. I just drove Fort Hill,
checking the cell towers.
It looked fine.
Also, all the radios
aren't working.
So what? So what? This
is... This is them?
All of it? Some
kind of scrambler?
[Luke] Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Because that...
that's what they do.
I need to get him
out of town, okay?
And Drew shot Ashworth?
-Drew shot Ashworth?
-Yes.
-Why?
-Because it makes sense
to have one in the
local cops, okay?
Maybe more than one.
Look, I don't understand
it all, either.
-Yeah.
-But you know...
you know, uh, that reporter?
-Kate whoever?
-Kate Nilson.
She tried to kill us, too.
[Luke] No, no, no. That's true.
Okay? She worked
for the Institute.
Okay, you have absolutely
no reason to believe me,
but we are telling
you the truth.
[Wendy exhaling sharply]
Yeah? [sighing]
What do you want?
I understand Dixon damaged
the deprivation tank.
"Damaged"? He blasted it apart.
You have any idea what kind
of TK power that requires?
A full house on a Sparkler
Night can't do that.
It's orders of magnitude
bigger than what we've seen.
You told us TK was too
weak to be weaponized.
It always was! It's not just me.
All of us. All the literature.
No one has ever had
a TK that strong,
not that could be verified.
Of course, there
were always rumors.
Presents some
intriguing new options.
There's no options!
We're simply not prepared to
deal with that kind of power.
Dixon's a time bomb.
We can't leave him like this.
Don't tell me liquidation.
[Sighing]
It would be safest.
But no, at the
moment, we need him.
So... we Gork him.
Immediately.
He conducts tonight, goes
straight to Recovery.
He can power The
Hum indefinitely.
The answer to our prayers.
Hey.
You better hurry up and eat.
I'm shutting this up soon.
It's Sparkler Night.
Here we go, Sha. Here
comes the airplane.
Come on, Sha.
You can't do Sparkler
Night on an empty stomach.
Oh, shit.
Avery, my man.
[Avery, telepathically]
What's wrong with Kalisha?
She's going, man.
They're all going.
Then me, then you.
Gorked.
Nicky, help me. Hold my hand.
[Nicky, telepathically]
What do you want me to do?
Just help me.
Kalisha.
Can you hear me?
[Nicky] Kalisha.
[Avery] Kalisha.
[Kalisha, telepathically]
Go away. I have to hide.
[Nicky] Wake up,
Kalisha, please.
-[Avery] Sha?
-[Nicky] Please, Kalisha.
[Avery] Kalisha.
[gagging, coughing]
[gagging]
Hey, look who it is.
It's Avester.
You're a sight for sore
eyes. I missed you.
I missed you too.
Someone give me a smoke. Today.
[Joanne exhaling sharply]
It's Sparkler Night. Eat up.
[Kalisha] Did Luke escape?
I felt it.
[Avery] Yeah, he's out.
They're scared shitless.
[Kalisha] I thought so.
I thought I felt him go.
-Fuck, yeah.
-Shh.
[Kalisha] Can you talk to him?
[Avery] I can feel
him sometimes.
He's not strong enough
to talk back to me.
But me... I'm strong.
I'm a lot stronger
than they know.
Strong enough to do something.
[Kalisha] We can't
escape, Avery.
[Avery] I have the pieces.
I don't know how to
put them together.
Thank you.
Ah, okay, so, we are
gonna run out of time
because they, uh...
they are not dumb.
-Just a minute.
-All right.
So, we... we head out,
stick to back roads.
-Yeah.
-Boston. Montreal.
-[Knocking]
-[Drew] Wendy? You in there?
-Wendy!
-[Wendy] Yeah, hold on.
-Let's go.
-No, no, no!
Go in here. Go in here.
Go on. We'll close it.
-[Drew] You all right?
-Hold on!
[exhaling sharply] I'm coming.
What's with the radios?
I tried changing the battery...
what are you doing, Drew?
What's going on? Sorry.
Who are you, exactly?
How many guesses do you need?
Oh, the FBI doesn't care
about warrants anymore?
[Sigsby] You're law enforcement.
Shouldn't take a warrant
to ensure your cooperation.
With what?
What are you doing, Drew?
[Sigsby] What's the last
you hear from Tim Jamieson?
Tim? Why? Is there
something wrong?
Afraid so. Last contact?
Uh, last night, he
borrowed my car.
-[door closing]
-Tell you why he needed it?
Why are you asking me about Tim?
[Sigsby] He may have had a...
a breakdown... of some kind.
A breakdown?
A break with reality.
There's substantial mental
illness in his family history.
How the fuck do you know that?
Wendy. Tim shot Chief Ashworth.
That's not possible.
Okay? No way.
It's true. We were
just at the station.
The Chief told you Tim shot him?
Chief didn't tell us
anything. Chief is dead.
What?
I'm sorry, Wendy.
I'm really sorry.
Oh, my God. Well, what's
Amanda going to do?
She... this... this... this
doesn't make any sense.
Well, it's...
He's the prime
suspect at this point.
I'm telling you, Wendy, I saw
him on my way out this morning.
It sounded like he'd been
drinking Annie's Kool-Aid,
talking about astronauts,
a hole in the moon.
Well, I still don't believe it.
And even if it's true, it
doesn't change the fact
that he's not in
my fucking house!
So, if you two don't mind...
Drew, get the fuck out!
Drew, what the
fuck are you doing?
Hey, Drew.
Ah! Ah! Hands.
Let's not make this worse.
It's already worse.
Back up against the
wall, both of you.
Hands where I can see them.
You won't...
-[Gun firing]
-[Gasping]
Sure, I will.
Ah! Jesus, Tim!
I told you, he's gone crazy!
We have to do something!
Shut up! Just shut up!
You shot the Chief
right in front of us,
so don't fuck with me.
That's her, the one
I told you about.
Mm-hmm.
Luke. I'm worried about you.
Wendy, if you wouldn't mind
taking these two into the
other room and tying them up,
relieving them of their weapons.
[exhaling sharply]
Don't tell me you're buying
this bullshit they're spinning.
How long have we
known each other?
-He's snapped!
-[Tim] Move!
All right, all right, all right.
There's no point arguing.
Let's de-escalate, right?
Like they taught us. There!
There! Come on. Have
everyone calm down.
Let's let Tim calm down.
We'll sort all this out.
Let's just... Let's just not
point guns at each other.
Tim.
Tim, look at me.
Let me disarm both of you, okay?
I'll establish chain-of-custody
on Drew's sidearm,
and forensics will show if
it's what killed the Chief.
There's not got gonna be
any forensics, right, Drew?
I'm sure the Chief's
body's already gone.
Still, I would be very
happy to put this gun down,
just as soon as you disarm
him and Miss FBI over there.
She's not FBI.
It's a good time to
de-escalate, like she said.
Drew?
Okay.
-[Gasping]
-[Tim] Hey! Hey! Hey!
Let her go! Let her go now!
Let her go right now, man!
[Wendy gasping]
[Wendy breathing heavily]
Drew. Drew, Drew, Drew.
Just give me a reason.
Mm.
I know this must feel like
a very dark time for you.
Give me it.
[breathing unsteadily]
Clearly, he's been
telling you things...
Yeah, no shit. You
kill Annie yourself?
-[Wendy] Tim?
-What?
You killed Drew.
He killed the Chief
and he just shot me.
I know. I've known him
since we were kids.
Mr. Jamieson,
I haven't killed anyone.
You're making a huge mistake,
and based on what?
The words of a scared,
confused child.
Maureen made a video.
Oh, well...
[sighing] That's unfortunate.
Why?
It means we're all dead.
Yeah?
What was on this video?
All of it.
Your...
"Gorks." All of it.
I think it went all
the way through.
Arm works fine.
[breathing unsteadily]
All right, let me take a look.
I told him everything.
No, you didn't.
[Luke] What does that mean?
-You don't know everything.
-I know...
what you do to us, kids like me,
like Kalisha, like Avery,
and I know what you
did to my parents.
Yeah, but you don't know why.
Smartest kid in the world
doesn't think to ask why.
What's to know? You're using us
to commit the perfect crime...
murders with no
physical evidence.
You're... You're a hit
squad. you're assassins
or whatever you wanna call it.
And you're the blind
man who felt the tail
and thought he could
describe the whole elephant.
We should just shoot her.
It's... not as
easy as you think.
She'll kill all
of us, if she can.
No. Not all of you.
Not if I don't have to.
Go ahead. Describe the elephant.
What's the point?
You're gonna kill me anyway.
Not if I don't have to.
I'm going for my cigarette.
Mm-hmm.
Yes.
Yes, the Institute is involved
in untraceable assassinations.
-I told you.
-Fucking A.
But the real question
is who we target.
Why does that matter?
You... you think we
do this for money?
Or politics?
You've seen the news
about Senator Ramsey,
died in a small
plane crash recently?
-Yeah, I heard that was you.
-Yeah.
Ramsey's what we call a "hinge."
If he'd lived, nine
years from now,
he's Secretary of Defense,
has a break with reality,
convinces the President
to hit North Korea,
limited nuclear strike.
The problem is, the missiles
overfly Russian airspace,
and Russian
early-warning systems
are old and shitty,
and from their
screens, it looks like
we're coming for them.
They have moments to
react. They launch.
We have moments
to react to that.
-We launch.
-Did you say,
"Nine years from now"?
Give or take.
-[Tim] Uh-huh.
-[Sigsby] I know.
Hard to fathom.
But I'm sure you've seen by now,
Luke has some rare
abilities, low level.
But there's another ability,
more rare, more important...
precognition.
Like telling the future?
The PC track.
How rare?
I'm not cleared to know how
many we have at any given time.
How many you have to do what?
Find people who will
trigger Armageddon.
Hinges, Tim.
Very good.
And once you've found one,
you put together
a target package,
and they turn over to
you for elimination.
Right?
Since 1950, we've
saved the world,
I don't know, over 500 times.
Yes, people have died, but
billions have been saved.
So, you're the math whiz.
You understand
cost-benefit ratios.
This is... it's bullshit.
It's fucking bullshit.
Okay. Well, what would
you do? What would you do?
What would you do
to save the world?
Whatever it takes?
Correct.
I don't get to have
crises of conscience.
I don't get to...
to feel sad for
some particular kid
and his poor, particular
grieving Mommy,
or the mission fails.
And full nuclear exchange?
Four billion people
die in two hours.
Within ten years,
throw in 99 percent
of plants and...
animals, if you care
about that kind of thing.
Yeah.
You can see my
thoughts. Am I lying?
She's not lying.
[Tim] That just means
she believes it.
So, tell me this.
If you really are
saving the world,
why not do it out in the open?
Why all the secrecy? Why
not let us all decide?
[Sigsby] We can't run that risk.
You understand that.
You shot a child in Boston
to prevent a massacre.
You walk out of here
with Luke Ellis,
you're putting the entire
world on suicide watch.
[dramatic music]
♪♪♪